All right, we'll start. Okay, so בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. We're going
to start
today's דף Daf is, today's דף Daf is קמ"א, Kuf Mem Aleph,
and we start on the ק"מ עמוד ב' Kuf Mem Amud Bet
on the משנה. Mishna. Again, קמ"א Kuf Mem Aleph is the דף,
Daf, 141. We start on ק"מ עמוד ב', Kuf Mem Amud Bet,
the משנה, Mishna, and we are in the middle of
שילוח הקן, Shiluach Haken, and we discussed the question
about about a כשר Kosher bird on a non-כשר Kosher egg, non-כשר
Kosher bird on a כשר Kosher egg, but certainly but the sense
was whether a כשר Kosher bird on a different species of כשר
Kosher would be חייב. Chayav. Anyway, now we pick up with the
new point in the משנה. Mishna.
היתה מעופפת, Hayeta me'ofefes, it was hovering over. So what defines, you
know, it says והאם רובצת על האפרוחים או על הביצים. Ve'ha'eim rovetzes
al ha'efrochim o al habetzim. So רובצת Rovetzes literally means crouching down
on, and from here they understand that it has to really be
directly on top of. If you remember yesterday, we discussed what happens
even if there's some physical barrier. So this משנה Mishna discusses, right,
how how over on top of it one would be obligated. So
if it was flying over, בזמן שכנפיה נוגעות בקן, Bizman she'knafeha nog'os
baken, if its if its wings actually are touching, I guess when
it's flapping down, are touching the nest itself, חייב, Chayav, I assume
or the chicks, true, correct, correct, then you're obligated.
חייב לשלח. Chayav l'shaleach. אין כנפיה נוגעות בקן, Ein knafeha nog'os baken,
if its high up enough that its wings do not touch it,
פטור מלשלח Patur m'lishaleach you are exempt, that it's not והאם רובצת.
Ve'ha'eim rovetzet.
אין שם אלא אפרוח אחד או ביצה אחת, Ein sham ela efroach
echad o beitzo achas, if there's only one chick or one or
one egg, even though it says אפרוחים Efrochim and ביצים, Betzim, חייב
לשלח Chayav l'shaleach you have to, שנאמר Shene'emar as as it says,
and this was quoted in the ברייתא Braita before, קן. Kan. It
says a a nest, קן מכל מקום, Kan mikol makom, whatever is
in the nest, even if it's not multiple chicks or eggs. Obviously
it has to be at least one. היו שם אפרוחים מפריחין, Hayu
sham efrochim mafriachin, let's say there were eggs there were chicks that
were able to fly by themselves already, או ביצים מוזרות, O betzim
muzaros, or eggs that were non-fertilized,
פטור מלשלח Patur m'lishaleach you're exempt, שנאמר Shene'emar והאם רובצת על האפרוחים
או על הביצים, Ve'ha'eim rovetzes al ha'efrochim o al habetzim, the mother
is crouching over the eggs or over the over the chicks, chicks
or eggs I should say. מה אפרוחים בני קיימא, Ma efrochim bnei
kayama, so we link them two ways: the same way chicks is
something that is alive, אף ביצים נמי בני קיימא, Af betzim nami
bnei kayama, so eggs have to mean that they'll be able to
give life, so they have to be fertilized eggs. יצאו מוזרות Yatzyu
muzaros to exclude cases of non-fertilized eggs. And we make the the
connection the reverse as well. ומה הביצים צריכין לאמן, U'mah habetzim tzrichin
l'imam, the same way eggs require their mother, אף אפרוחים נמי צריכין
לאמן, Af efrochim nami tzrichin l'imam, also chicks are only chicks that
require their mother, יצאו מפריחין, Yatzyu mafriachin, which excludes the case of
of those that are already able to fly.
Yes, גמרא Gemara or Aramaic, you know, it has קיימא Kayama in
there, that's an Aramaic word.
That's a good point, that's a very good point, you're right. Normally
you would not have any any Aramaic. I also think you say
it's strange because it has the דרשה Drasha embedded in it, and
that's also less common.
Yes, exactly.
Right, we do have a few of those. Absolutely, it is rare,
but we do have had them now a few times. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan:
רובצת, Rovetzes, so literally the verse says literally crouching, ולא מעופפת, V'lo
me'ofefes, not just flying over. יכול אפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן, Yachol afilu
knafeha nog'os baken, maybe it means even if it's hovering very close
and the wings are touching the the nest, it would be excluded.
תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar רובצת. Rovetzes. No, רובצת Rovetzes includes that. גמרא
G'mora says, מאי תלמודא? Mai talmuda? Where do you derive it? Where
do you see רובצת Rovetzes includes hovering as long as it's very
closely hovering? So מדלא כתיב יושבת Mi-d'lo ketiv yosheves because it didn't
literally say sitting on the eggs, but רובצת, Rovetzes, crouching. You know,
when you crouch over things that you're sort of crouched down, but
you're not your rear isn't necessarily on top of it, you're crouched.
So therefore if it's crouched on it, it means that it doesn't
have to be touching, it could be directly above, and therefore that
would include even flying as long as its wings were touching were
touching.
And certainly if it were sitting.
Certainly if it were sitting. Yeah. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב: Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: so רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says in the name of רב, Rav, היתה יושבת בין שני
רובדי אילן. Hayeta yosheves bein shnei rovdai ilan. Let's say it was
on two branches. Okay, you got two branches, you know, sometimes you
have these like games where you try to like,
support an egg between two sticks. I don't know, I mean, you
know what I mean, like try to move it? Anyway, so the
so the chicken or whatever it is, the the bird is a
mother bird is on two branches, and the eggs are directly over
it. Okay, so it's not flying, it's not crouching, directly under it.
It's not flying, it's not crouching, it's sitting but it's sitting suspended
over. Okay, now presumably we learned before that if there was literally
like a full type of a division, you know, that was so
dividing it, then it would not be considered over, but here there
is air space underneath the mother's bottom and the eggs, but it's
being held up by these two parallel branches. Okay, so what is
the
הלכה? Halakha? היתה יושבת בין שני רובדי אילן, Hayeta yosheves bein shnei
rovdai ilan, between two like branches of a tree. רואין, Ro'in, you
look. כל שאם תשמט, Kol she-im tishameit, if you were to remove
the branch... נופלת עליהן nophetet aleihen then she would fall on top
of the eggs, then חייב לשלח chayav leshale'ach you are obligated. That's
considered to be רובצת. rovetzet. ואם לאו ve'im lav and if not
פטור patur you are exempt. Now that's pretty interesting because that even
suggests even if it was very high up which would be strange.
I mean if she's literally flying we say she has to be
very close. So here too why should it matter? So let's assume
maybe that's not true. Let's assume that it is that she is
physically close but I still might have thought the branches are a
הפסק hefsek and it says no as long as they're sort of
parallel not together and as long as were you to remove it
she would fall directly on that is considered רובצת. rovetzet.
So it does you know it is an interesting question let's say
she's you know ten levels up.
I understand so I would like to assume for argument's sake that
that's not the case that the only issue here because we already
said she has to be within the wings have to be able
to touch but the only issue here is that it's even more
of a division you've got these branches.
So you're saying that her wings are able to touch from that
distance.
That's how I would like to read it. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. מיתיבי Meitivei I'll ask you on this. היתה
יושבת ביניהן haita yoshevet beineihen פטור מלשלח. patur mishale'ach. If she is
sitting between the eggs she's in the actual nest itself and she
has an egg on each side of her so you're exempt because
she's not on top of she's not crouching on top of she's
just between them. Okay so פטור. patur. על גביהן al gabeihen if
she's sitting on them חייב לשלח chayav leshale'ach you have to. היתה
מעופפת haita meofefet if she was hovering now this is against our
משנה. Mishna. אפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן afilu knafeha nogot baken even if
the wings touch the the the nest פטור מלשלח patur mishale'ach you're
exempt. So the גמרא Gemara says we're going to get to that
in a minute but first let's focus on the first half. מאי
לאו על גביהן דומיא דביניהן mai lav al gabeihen dumya debeineihen when
it says sitting on them isn't that similar to sitting between them?
מה ביניהן דנגע בהו ma beineihen denaga behu the same way when
it says sitting between them she's exempt means even if she's touching
them because she's between it's she's exempt. So therefore by parallel אף
על גביהן af al gabeihen when it says on them that she's
obligated דנגע בהו denaga behu it means that she's literally touching because
parallel to sitting where she's touching sitting between so sitting on top
also would require literally touching. אבל רובדי אילן aval rovdei ilan if
she's separated by these branches פטור patur presumably you'd be exempt. So
you know by the parallel of the case of between presumably she
has to be sitting literally on. הגמרא Gemara says לא lo not
necessarily. על גביהן דומיא דביניהן al gabeihen dumya debeineihen I will agree
that on top is similar to between but what's the case of
between? מה ביניהן דלא נגע עלייהו ma beineihen dela naga aleihu the
case of sitting between the case is not that she you emphasized
she's touching them even though she's sitting between I'll emphasize the opposite
she's sitting between she's not touching the top of them she might
be touching the side but she's not touching the top of the
egg. So אף על גביהן af al gabeihen even when it says
on top of them it would be sufficient דלא נגע עלייהו dela
naga aleihu even if she's not touching the tops. And how could
she be sitting on without touching the tops? That she's supported והיינו
רובדי אילן vehainu rovdei ilan supported by these branches. So the גמרא
Gemara says you know what הכי נמי מסתברא hachi nami mistavra your
way of reading actually makes sense. די סלקא דעתך רובדי אילן פטור
dei salka daitach rovdei ilan patur if the case of the branches
the you know the parallel branches you're exempt
אדמתני היתה מעופפת אפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן פטור מלשלח admitani haita meofefet
afilu knafeha nogot baken patur mishale'ach since the end of the ברייתא
Braita arguing with our משנה Mishna seemingly says that if she's hovering
even if the wings touch she's exempt מלשלח. mishale'ach. ליתני litni tell
me a bigger חידוש. chidush. Forget hovering רובדי אילן rovdei ilan even
if she's sitting as long as it's on the branches she would
you would be exempt וכל שכן מעופפת vechol shekein meofefet how much
more so if it's not even sitting if it's just hovering. So
therefore from the fact that it goes to the example of hovering
to exempt you suggests that sitting even on these parallel branches you'd
be obligated.
But wait if she's
sitting but the גמרא Gemara says wait let's just read the answer.
מעופפת אצטריכא ליה. meofefet itztricha lei. No there's a reason maybe sitting
on the branches you'd also be exempt. So why is it going
to the point of hovering?
דאפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן פטור מלשלח dafilu knafeha nogot baken patur mishale'ach
to tell you against our משנה Mishna that hovering even if she's
touching because there's an element of touching that you have in the
hovering case that you don't have in the sitting case. What element
of touching do you have? That the wings touch the nest. So
I might have thought that in that case you'd be obligated even
if in the sitting with the parallel branches you're exempt. So it
tells me that case you're also exempt so you can't prove it
from this ברייתא. Braita. This ברייתא Braita does not address explicitly the
case of the branches of the trees. It talks about sitting on
sitting between hovering. We don't know still what the story would be
about the parallel branches. Now let's try to reconcile it with our
משנה. Mishna. והנן תנן vahanan tnan does as our משנה Mishna teach
בזמן שכנפיה נוגעות בקן חייב לשלח bizman sheknafeha nogot baken chayav leshale'ach
that when it touches when it's hovering and touching the wings touch
you're obligated. אמר רבי ירמיה כי תניא מתניתין בנוגעת מן הצד amar
Rabi Yirmiya ki tanyah matnitin benoga'at min hatzad our ברייתא Braita when
it says hovering you're exempt is talking that you are touching only
from the side and you are not touching actually the the the
tops of the of the of the eggs. So רש"י Rashi actually
says here I mean normally when you say touching the nest you
assume that's exactly what it means like if this גמרא Gemara was
the nest you'd assume that the wings would come down and be
hitting the sides. But because of this contradiction and to reconcile it
we seem to be reinterpreting the word nest to mean eggs and
to say that if her wings are touching the sides of the
egg she's exempt but if the wings actually you know sort of
brush over the tops of the eggs that's like sitting on top
of the eggs and therefore you'd Therefore she's obligated. Okay, that's if
you take a look at רש״י, Rashi, right? רש״י Rashi says
מן הצד, min hatzad, two lines down on the wide lines,
שנוגעות בצידי. she-nogot b'tzidei.
Oh no, I'm sorry. I'm sorry. I think that's the earlier רש״י.
Rashi. One minute. No, no, no, I think that's right.
No, no, no, I'm sorry. That's the earlier גמרא Gemara from מן
הצד, min hatzad, excuse me. That's the גמרא Gemara about when she's
sitting next to them. So not about not about the case about
the wings. So it's not exactly clear, but the only way I
can imagine this is that if it's distinguishing between touching the sides
of the קן kan and touching the top of the קן, kan,
it could literally mean whether her wings are brushing over the top
of the actual nest, like the twigs that make up the nest,
but I do wonder if at this stage the גמרא's Gemara shifting
to say that the קן kan here is referring, you know, to
the eggs. It's the side of the nest and the top
of the nest?
Yeah, that's what it says the גמרא Gemara what because well, if
you understand it in the same way we just said that if
you're sitting between the eggs that you're exempt and only if you're
sitting on, והיא רובצת על האפרוחים או על הביצים, v'hi rovetzet al
ha'efrochim o al habeitzim, right, on top of, not on the side
of. So when we are including in the concept of רובצת, rovetzet,
crouching over, the idea of hovering with the wings, that that's like
crouching over, we demand the same type of idea. We demand that
it be on and not considered on the side. Okay, but nevertheless
you would think that if she's physically directly above and the wings,
you know, encompass the sides of the nest, that's like you are
you are on top of the eggs or the chicks. Here it
seems to be that the wings have to actually touch not just
the sides of the nest, but either either again I it's a
little ambiguous how to read it, but either the top of the
nest itself, like brushing over the top surface of the nest, or
which I think makes a little more sense to interpret it at
this stage, to mean the top of the eggs or the top
of the chicks.
So she's actually sitting in the nest? Right. But if she's if
her wings are touching the nest but not the eggs at all,
then you're exempt from sending her?
Well again, I'm not sure how to read it about what do
you call it, אפי׳ גביהן דלא נגע. afilu gabeihen d'lo naga. One
minute,
where's the גמרא? Gemara?
Did I skip? Anyway, no, it says בנוגע מן הצד. benogeya min
hatzad. Yeah, I mean the גמרא Gemara says there בנוגע מן הצד
benogeya min hatzad you're exempt. So the question is just how do
you read בנוגע מן הצד? benogeya min hatzad? What does מן הצד
min hatzad mean? I mean what do you need in terms of
the touching of the wings to be חייב? chayav? Clearly some type
of touching above, but I think it's a little unclear whether touching
above means touching above on the nest or touching above on the
eggs.
Well that's what I'm saying, if you're touching above on the nest
you'd say, all right fine, you're not actually touching the eggs. If
she's touching the eggs even from the side, you can say then
certainly—no,
that was the earlier part of the רישא. reisha. If she's even
sitting in the nest, if she's touching them on the sides, you're
exempt. That was earlier in the משנה Mishnah and the ברייתא.
Baraita. Yeah, and what kind of bird do they have in mind?
Because this is a if it's a sparrow,
by the fall they couldn't wouldn't touch the side of the nest
because the nest is so big. I was just wondering what size
kind of any or they're just trying to get the argument what
whether the nest is separate from the bird?
Yeah, well that's the question, defining something that satisfies the פסוק pasuk
about רובצת על, rovetzet al, crouching on. So you need the concept
of crouching and you need it to be over and on the
side. Actually I'm looking back, I see I was right initially with
the רש״י. Rashi. This מן הצד min hatzad does seem to be
going on this answer of the hovering, and רש״י Rashi does use
the plural, שנוגעות בצידיהן ולא על גביהן. she-nogot b'tzideihen v'lo al gabeihen.
So it does seem that רש״י Rashi is saying that when we're
talking about we're saying that even though the wings touching is not
enough, that it be on the side, it has to be on
the top, that now we're switching from talking about the nest to
talking about the eggs or the chicks, which makes sense and we're
being consistent. So she can't be next to the chicks or the
eggs, she has to be over, and then we and even when
it's the wings, we're saying that the wings have to actually touch
the tops of them, not the sides of them. And the one
question we haven't decided is what if it's being separated by these
parallel branches. Let's just read this again, now we're going to do
the same thing in reverse. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri,
some start try to prove it from the assume that this ברייתא
Baraita initially was a proof, not initially was a question. לימא מסייע
ליה, leima mesayei lei, let's support you. היתה יושבת ביניהם פטורה מלשלח.
haytah yoshevet beineihem peturah m'lishalei'ach. So between them you're exempt. על גביהן
חייב לשלח. al gabeihen chayav l'shalei'ach. So over them you're obligated. היתה
מעופפת אפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן פטורה מלשלח. haytah me'ofefet afilu knafeha nogot
b'kan peturah m'lishalei'ach. If it was hovering, even if the wings are
touching, you're exempt. מאי לאו על גביהן דומיא דביניהם? mai lav al
gabeihen dumya d'beineihem? Does not over them when you're obligated similar to
next to them? מה ביניהם דלא נגע עלייהו? mah beineihem d'lo naga
alei'hu? So the same way next to them means you're not touching
their top, אף על גביהן דלא נגע עלייהו, af al gabeihen d'lo
naga alei'hu, even on them when you're obligated would be a scenario
where it's not touching the top. והיינו רובדי אילן, v'hainu rovdei ilan,
and that would be the scenario of what's over them without touching
the top: the parallel branches. הגמרא ha-Gemara says לא, lo, no, that's
not the way to read it. על גביהן דומיא דביניהם. al gabeihen
dumya d'beineihem. Yes, on is like by the side, but here's how
the comparison should be read: מה ביניהם דנגע בהו אף על גביהן
דנגע בהו. mah beineihem d'naga behu af al gabeihen d'naga behu. The
same way between them is touching regardless of top or side, then
on top you're obligated when you are touching, but the natural touching.
What's the natural touching? Which is you are physically the rear is
on top, the bottom is on top of the eggs. אבל רובדי
אילן, aval rovdei ilan, the parallel branches, פטור, patur, you'd be exempt.
So therefore you don't know how to how to what to infer
about the parallel branches. Are you exempt because you're not touching the
top or are you obligated because you don't need to touch the
top as long as you're above? So the גמרא Gemara says no.
אי הכי הא דקתני סיפא, iy hachi ha d'katani seifa, since if
that's true, why did the end have to go to extreme and
say היתה מעופפת אפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן פטור, haitah meofefet afilu knafeha
nogot b'kan patur, that if it's hovering, you're exempt even if its
wings touch? If it's true, ליתני רוב דאילן, lisni rov de'ilan, why
didn't you tell me even if it's on the parallel branches, וכל
שכן מעופפת, v'chol sheken meofefet, and certainly hovering? Right, if in the
case of sitting you're exempt, certainly hovering. גמרא Gemara says no, מעופפת
איצטריכא ליה, meofefet itztriecha leh, I might have thought that you would
be exempt by the parallel branches and maybe even obligated by the
hovering. Why? דאפילו כנפיה נוגעות בקן פטור מלשלח, d'afilu knafeha nogot b'kan
patur m'lishaleach, because there I might have thought that hey, that has
something that the sitting doesn't have. There there is some physical contact.
The wings are touching. So therefore it had to tell me that
even that case you're exempt. Fine. So we still don't know the
story about the parallel branches. We know that sitting on the side
is exempt. We know that hovering is,
אמימר Ameimar says חייב, chayav, this says פטור. patur. What's the difference
again? Let's take, let's see it again. So the גמרא Gemara says,
והנן תנן בזמן שכנפיה נוגעות בקן חייב לשלח, v'hanan tnan bizman sheknafeha
nogot b'kan chayav l'shaleach, don't we say when the wings touch you're
obligated? אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, כי קתני מתניתין בנוגע מן
הצד. ki katani masnitin b'nogea min hatzad. No, when is our, what
are we talking about when you're only touching the side? So when
you're touching the side then of what we said, but again רש"י
Rashi from, if my inference from רש"י Rashi is correct, it seems
like he is going exactly from on this phrase מן הצד min
hatzad because I don't think the phrase מן הצד min hatzad applied,
was stated
before. It just said ביניהן. beineihen. Right, so yeah, רש"י Rashi clearly
is talking about that, right. So therefore, yes, when you're touching the
side then you're exempt, that's like sitting by the side, it's only
when you're touching on top that you would be obligated, yes.
I'm not sure why this question is bothering me now because the
גמרא Gemara frequently reinterprets פסוקים psukim to the extent that you can't
recognize them anymore. Right. And here is certainly a case. But maybe
it's because of the move back to kind of in the background
is the idea of על קן ציפור יגיעו רחמיך al kan tzipor
yagiu rachamecha and the criticism in other places of טעמי המצוות. ta'amei
hamitzvos. Right.
So, am I, you're that it's too technical these distinctions and it's,
right I was waiting to hear that question from Rivka. I know,
I know. So yeah, so the point is like this, right, I
mean I think that this מצוה, mitzvah, it's a little funny because
on the one hand this מצוה mitzvah we all assume that the
reason is transparent. But the reason actually is not transparent at all,
I should mention. You know the גמרא Gemara says that somebody who
says על קן ציפור יגיעו רחמיך משתקין אותו. al kan tzipor yagiu
rachamecha mashtakin oso. And one of the explanations, the one most quoted
in the גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berachos is why, because שעושה גזירותיו
של הקדוש ברוך הוא רחמים ואינן אלא גזירות, she'oseh gezeirosov shel Hakadosh
Baruch Hu rachamim v'einan ela gezeiros, because he makes God's mitzvos as
if they're about compassion and they're really only decrees. So what does
that mean? Does it mean it's not about compassion? So the רמב"ם
Rambam says well that's an opinion that says that we don't, we
don't try to understand טעמי המצוות, ta'amei hamitzvos, we look at them
as all arbitrary. We don't rule that way of course we believe
that there are reasons and we try to understand the reasons and
of course this reason is about compassion. That's what the רמב"ם Rambam
says. But the רמב"ן Ramban says it's really not about compassion for
the birds because actually if you think about it, I don't think
the רמב"ן Ramban says this point but I'll add this point, if
you think about it it's not so compassionate to be chasing away
the mother bird as she's trying to get her eggs and you're
chasing her away, she's undergoing a lot of suffering that way. Maybe
if you would just שחט shecht her you'd put her out of
her suffering right away. So he says it's not about that we
care that we, God cares about the suffering of animals. God cares
about humans and גזירה gezeira means because you make decrees about your
subjects, so God cares about humans and he cares that the act
of doing this makes us callous and cruel and not so much
because we're causing the suffering of the animal but because we're wiping
out an entire family. It's like אותו ואת בנו oso v'es b'no
and that breeds cruelty and callousness within us. So that's what the
רמב"ן Ramban says. The ספר החינוך Sefer Hachinuch says, because ספר החינוך
Sefer Hachinuch is always very interested in very sort of more theological
aspects, he interprets this not about, not about moral issues. He says
that by seeing that God does not want to wipe out an
entire family of animals, it reinforces our belief about השגחה hashgacha and
God's concern about the world and about the survival of the world
and about species and about השגחה פרטית hashgacha pratis and it makes
us more appreciate God's involvement in our lives. So if, so something
which we think the reason is so transparent, we have three very
different explanations there. So that's just number one on the one hand,
you know, it is true that the מצוה mitzvah of שלוח הקן
shiluach hakan because the גמרא Gemara in ברכות, Berachos, the משנה Mishna
in ברכות Berachos says that somebody who says this is about God's
compassion you silence him because becomes a, you're normally like a interesting
central sort of sort of center
of focus of discussing issues of טעמי המצוות. ta'amei hamitzvos. But the
first thing to note is that the טעמי המצוות ta'amei hamitzvos of
this מצוה mitzvah itself are not as transparent as we would think.
That being said, I do agree that there does seem to be
something whatever, whatever the reason is it does seem to be something
that at least speaks to larger values although we can debate what
those larger values are. And in that context to see all of
these sort of technical hair-splitting things which are not more than they
are anywhere else, right, anywhere else the גמרא Gemara also is very
formalistic. It says this so it has to be this way and
not that way, like we had the problem before about making a
fence on your roof. You don't have to do it if it's
a, if it's a study hall even though there are thousands of
people there because it's not a normal domicile. The גמרא Gemara is
often making, is very much about formal issues, and yes, I do
admit that it is a definite challenge when the focus about sort
of
formal definitions
and criteria seem to not take into account the larger values that
are at stake and seem to just be about well this is
the exact parameters of the מצוה. mitzvah. So I don't really have
a great answer to that. I will say that I wrote an
article recently that was published in the Saul Berman Festschrift which talks
about the relationship between the sort of formalistic arguments and formal parameters
and to the degree that they are in conversation with the טעמי
המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot in the context of the question about דרשינן טעמא
דקרא darshinan ta'ama dikra or לא דרשינן טעמא דקרא lo darshinan ta'ama
dikra and whether those two ever really are in conversation or not
and what are some of the parameters of them. But yes, it
is correct to say that the גמרא Gemara is much much more
formalistic than it is about sort of like let's just talk about
what the values are here and define things in terms of the
values. So I don't have a good explanation other than that's the
nature of the הלכתי halakhic process that it's in that and I'm
sure that if you go to this, you go to a judge
or the Supreme Court, they also don't just say let's ignore the
exact language of the statute and let's get to the heart of
what it's about, right? There's always you fundamentally first work with the
language of the statute but it's in some type of a
conversation and maybe that's the problem, not that it is formalistic but
it doesn't even seem to be in any conversation with the values.
And that I do admit is definitely an accurate description and the
problem.
Yes. And it refers to God as
compassion, רחם, rachem, חמול על מעשיך, chamol al ma'asecha, not only on
human beings. So that's the גמרא Gemara seems to be totally disconnected.
It's like they're going out of their way to disconnect
compassion from this מצוה. mitzvah. Right. I mean, that's a good, you
mean going back to that משנה Mishnah in ברכות Berachot that it's
if you say על קן ציפור יגיעו רחמיך. al kan tzippor yagi'u
rachamecha. Right,
right. And ורחמיו על כל מעשיו verachamav al kol ma'asav and so
on. Although interestingly the גמרא Gemara does debate whether the idea of
צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim is דאורייתא de'oraita or not, because
that implicitly acknowledges that you could say that all these מצוות mitzvot
even about animals ultimately are not about the suffering of animals per
se but like the רמב"ן Ramban says about us in various ways.
But you are correct, it is what why the גמרא Gemara is
trying to do that. Look, there's a general problem and I think
with this we'll have to go on, there's a general problem with
טעמי המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot which is the גמרא Gemara already says in
סנהדרין Sanhedrin which is that if you focus too much on טעמי
המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot then you say who cares about the details as
long as I'm satisfying the purpose of the
law. And then it speaks about like שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech and
he said I can do I can have many wives and not
go astray etc. So that always has been a challenge with a
discussion of
טעמי המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot and could be that that's why the גמרא
Gemara is very insistent on the formalist aspects. Don't think you know
what the reasons are, our focus is to make sure we know
what the law is and what our obligation is as a counterbalance
to saying that if we know what the reasons are then we
don't have to be as careful about the specifics of the law.
But I do understand the problem that it is you would have
expected at least more of a conversation than we're having. I get
it. Okay, one last point and then we have to go on.
Yes. Just about the answer. So when we say
תניא כוותיה דאיסי בן יהודה tanya kevateih de'Isi ben Yehuda that's when
you're פטור מן
השלח?
patur
min hashalach?
Yeah, yeah, I know it says מתניסן matnisan not מתניסין matnisin but
I believe that they're talking about the ברייתא braita that said you're
exempt. Okay, let's go on. אין שם אלא אפרוח, ein sham ela
efroach, if there is only one bird you're still obligated. אמרו ליה
רבנן לרבא, amru leih rabanan le-Rava, so what one of the rabbis
said to Rava, meaning one of the rabbinical students said to Rava,
אימא, eima, why not I say אימא איפכא, eima ipcha, say the
opposite. אין שם אפרוח אלא אחד או ביצה אחת פטור מלשלח, ein
sham efroach ela echad o beitzah achat patur milishaleach, דבעינן אפרוחים או
ביצים, deba'inan efrochim o beitzim, why not interpret the phrase chicks or
eggs literally that you need at least two? וליכא, velika, and you
don't have them, so one you'd be exempt. So the opposite of
what the משנה Mishnah says. And then do the opposite דרשה drasha
the other way. היו שם אפרוחים מפריחים או ביצים מוזרות חייב לשלח,
hayu sham efrochim mafrihim o beitzim muzarot chayav leshaleach, and maybe that
if the chicks are able to fly or if the eggs are
not fertile maybe you'd be obligated. שנאמר קן קן, shene'emar kan kan,
קן מכל מקום, kan mikol makom, it says a nest in regardless,
meaning it says in a nest so why and you interpret that
to include even one chick or one egg. Why not say the
opposite? A nest includes even if they're able to fly, even if
they're not fertile, okay, and but exclude the case of one chick
and one egg. So the גמרא Gemara says no. אם כן נכתוב
קרא ואם רובצת עליהם. im ken nichtov kra ve'im rovetzet aleihem. Then
it would not have had to specify אפרוחים או ביצים efrochim o
beitzim a second time. מאי ואם רובצת על האפרוחים או על הביצים?
mai ve'im rovetzet al ha'efrochim o al habeitzim? Why did it spell
out explicitly chicks and eggs the second time? לאקושי אפרוחים לביצים וביצים
לאפרוחים, le'akushi efrochim lebeitzim uveitzim le'efrochim, only to tell you that they
are linked. That an egg needs a quality of the chick, it
needs to be fertilized, and the chick needs a quality of the
egg, it needs to be able to have its mother. If they
did not need each other's qualities then the verse would have lumped
them together with one word of עליהם. aleihem. Okay, so that's that
משנה. Mishnah. Now we go on. Now we get more to defining
the actual definition of the מצוה mitzvah itself. Let's take a look.
שלחה וחזרה אפילו ארבע וחמישה פעמים חייב, shalcha vechazra afilu arba vechamishah
pe'amim chayav, שנאמר שלח תשלח את האם. shene'emar shaleach teshaleach et ha'em.
If you sent it and it came back then you have then
you keep you're still obligated. say oh I'm done, I sent it
away once. But שלח תשלח shaleach tishalach means even four, five times,
even a hundred times, if it keeps on flying back, you have
to keep on sending it away.
You haven't taken the eggs yet.
Well, why do you say that?
Because what would you be sending it away for if you'd already
taken the eggs?
Or is it you sent it away, you took the eggs, and
now it's flying back at you?
So you already took the eggs.
Oh, you're saying that maybe חזרה chazra is when it is still
in a context of רובצת. rovetzet.
Right, if it's חזרה chazra without a רובצת, rovetzet, that's interesting. I
have to see if that's discussed. I actually wasn't assuming that way.
I was assuming you sent it away, you grabbed the eggs, and
now it's coming back. But what you're saying is, but then you
don't have האם רובצת על האפרוחים. ha'em rovetzet al ha'efrochim. You're imagining
you sent it away, and then it flew back before you had
a chance to take the eggs, and you don't say, well, ignore
it now. What you're saying probably makes more sense. Okay,
let's take a look. Yes?
I mean, that goes back to what we were just discussing about
compassion and to
make, you know,
maybe the mother might sit there in mourning. I mean, if there's
such a thing. You know, maybe really to send it away is
to try to separate it totally from the experience.
Right.
So you're saying it comes back tomorrow and you see it's still...
No, no, no, I was imagining that it was still coming to
basically attack you. You grabbed the eggs, and it was coming back,
and it was attacking you, and that's the way I was imagining
it. But that would not be... You see, you're being a little
more formalistic here, which is probably why you're right. You were imagining
that it has to recreate the scenario of האם רובצת על האפרוחים.
ha'em rovetzet al ha'efrochim. And that's the statement in the משנה. mishna.
No,
no, no, the next statement... let's read the next statement. The next
statement is a little different. Okay. אמר הריני נוטל את האם ומשלח
את הבנים חייב. amar hareni notel et ha'em u'meshaleach et habanim chayav.
Now we discussed this yesterday. The משנה, mishna, the Torah says you
can't take both. What it does say is you take the chicks
and you don't take and you send away the mother. Let's say
you said, "I don't want the chicks, I'm interested in the mother."
So am I allowed to do that? Right? It's... on the one
hand, I'm not taking both, but on the other hand the Torah
says no, what you're supposed to do is take the chicks and
send away the mother. Do I have the option of taking the
mother and ignoring the chicks? So the משנה mishna says no. אמר
הריני נוטל את האם ומשלח את הבנים חייב. amar hareni notel et
ha'em u'meshaleach et habanim chayav. Even in that case, you're obligated. You
do not have an option of taking the mother. You have to,
in this scenario, send away the mother. שנאמר שלח תשלח את האם,
shene'emar shaleach tishalach et ha'em, send away the mother. Now, I should
say that there's an interesting discussion. The ספר החינוך Sefer Hachinuch says
that he thought, he initially thought that the פשט pshat was, that
let's say you did that, you took the mother and you did
not take the chicks. He thinks that, he initially thought that you're
only transgressing the positive מצוה mitzvah of שלח תשלח את האם. shaleach
tishalach et ha'em. You don't transgress the negative, because the negative מצוה
mitzvah is לא תקח האם על הבנים, lo tikach ha'em al habanim,
don't take them both. I didn't take them both, I just took
the mother. So there's a positive מצוה mitzvah to send away the
mother, but maybe I didn't transgress the negative. But he proves, based
on the גמרא Gemara and a lot of ראשונים, Rishonim, that that's
not true. That actually if you just take the mother, you transgress
לא תקח האם על הבנים. lo tikach ha'em al habanim. Why? Because
of how you read the word על. al. על al doesn't mean
"with" the children, it means don't take the mother who was hovering
over the chicks. So therefore, even if you just take the mother,
you transgress not only the positive, but even the negative.
So what if you actually want the mother? You send her away,
then, you know, then if she goes to the next tree, then
you take her?
Well, actually, yes. Ironically, that the way you're able to take the
mother is you take the chicks, the eggs, and send her away,
and then after you send her away, the next time she's not
hovering, then you're allowed to take her. Actually, technically, what you could
even do, you know, we'll see sort of a case like this
in the משנה, mishna, is, you know, if you take one of
like these tricks—though the גמרא Gemara left it בתיקו—is be'teiku you could
like spread a blanket over the nest so they technically wouldn't be...
or actually, what you do is you capture her when she's not
hovering. That's the easier thing. Right? The מצוה mitzvah is only, as
we saw, only if she's directly on top.
So you're annihilating a family in one day?
Yeah, that's again the irony, and that's the point we're making. There's
ways to completely violate whatever the values of the מצוה mitzvah here
are because of technicalities. So you can take the mother as long
as she's not hovering. So you grab the mother a foot away
from the nest, and then you grab the eggs, and that you're
allowed to do because she wasn't hovering over. Because you had a
specific order actually to snatch it. Right, exactly. Exactly. Okay. נטל את
הבנים והחזירן לה או והחזירן לכאן, natal et habanim vehachziran lah o
vehachziran lekan, so לכאן. lekan. Let's say you took the nest eggs,
you did the מצוה, mitzvah, or the mother wasn't hovering or whatever
and you took the eggs, and then afterwards you somehow, for whatever
bizarre reason, put them back in the nest, ואחר כך חזרה האם
עליהם, v'achar kach chazra ha'em aleihem, and now the mother is hovering
on them again, פטור מלשלח, patur melishaleach, you're exempt because that's the
issue we said before about מזומן. mezuman. Then the eggs are already
in your possession, and the Torah says כי יקרא, ki yikare, and
that would be an exemption that way.
In this the forest somewhere and then...
Yeah, the forest, you grab the eggs when the mother wasn't there,
or you did the מצוה mitzvah and you grabbed the eggs, and
then you put them back, then you're exempt. Oh, was that your
point about my scenario? Because that is sort of similar to my
scenario. If you're... oh, but you're thinking about the early bird. But
if you grab the eggs and you're covering and then the mother,
you know, again... that's your point, that it's no longer האם רובצת.
ha'em rovetzet. Now you have control over the eggs.
So you come back a few days later, you don't have to
do it again.
Yes, correct. Okay. Now, אמר ליה ההוא מרבנן לרבא. amar lei hahu
merabanan l'Rava. So one of the again rabbinical students, that's usually what
this means, said to Rava, ואימא שלח חדא זימנא תשלח תרי זימני.
v'eima shaleach chada zimna, tishalach trei zimnei. So שלח תשלח, shaleach tishalach,
I should say שלח, shaleach, means twice because it's double. And how
do we know? four five times? How do we know, you know,
an infinite number of times? אמר ליה *amlei* no, it's not because
it says תשלח *tishalach*. It's אמר ליה שלח shallach אפילו מאה פעמים
*amlei shaloch afilu meah pe'amim*. שלח shallach *shaloch* means send, you know,
that means without a limit. It doesn't mean just once. So we
don't, the idea of doing it multiple times we don't get from
the double language of תשלח *tishalach*. So what does תשלח *tishalach* mean?
So תשלח *tishalach*, so what is it telling me? אין לי אלא
לדבר הרשות *ein li ela lidvar ha-reshus*. I only know when you
need the birds for a, you know, for an optional thing.
לדבר מצווה מניין *lidvar mitzvah minayin*? How do I know that you
even have an obligation even if you're taking the bird for a
מצווה *mitzvah* purpose? תלמוד לומר תשלח מכל מקום *talmud lomar tishalach mikol
makom*. So the double language is regardless of why you're taking it.
Now, that's actually a משנה mishnah *mishnah* coming up which we'll see,
the next משנה mishnah *mishnah* says, not the next, whatever, two משניות
*mishnayos* says, that let's say you want to use the birds for
the טהרה *tahara* of the מצורע metzora, *metzora*. We're back to that
again, right? You want to use it for purifying the מצורע metzora
*metzora*. Let's say these are the only birds available to you for
whatever bizarre reason, the mother bird. In that type of a case,
can you take the mother bird even when she's hovering? So it
says no, in that case no, you're not allowed, you don't have
a special license even if you need it for a דבר מצווה
*dvar mitzvah*. שלח תשלח shallach teshallach? *shaloch tishalach* even for a דבר
מצווה *dvar mitzvah*. Now again, the scenario is pretty hard. First of
all, that there's no other bird. Second of all, even if there
are no other birds, just wait till she's not hovering. You know,
or throw a rock at her and make her not hover or
something. Well, that's actually an interesting question, could you do that? We're
actually going to have a case like that in a minute, right?
Could you, even if she is hovering, do something to make her
not hover and then exploit the opportunity. But anyway, it's a bizarre
scenario where this is your only option and even so you're obligated
to send her away. So now we're going to discuss that issue.
מכל מקום *mikol makom*. אמר ליה רב אבא בריה דרב יוסף בר
אבא לרב כהנא *amlei Rav Abba brei de-Rav Yosef bar Abba le-Rav
Kahana*. So רב אבא *Rav Abba* the son of רב יוסף *Rav
Yosef* said to
רב כהנא *Rav
Kahana*: אלא טעמא דכתב רחמנא תשלח *ella ta'ama de-ksav Rachmana tishalach*. It's
because it has the double language to tell you even for a
מצווה *mitzvah*. הא לאו הכי הוה אמינא לדבר מצווה לא *ha lav
hachi havah amina lidvar mitzvah lo*? Otherwise I would have thought that
for a מצווה *mitzvah* purpose you do not have, you are not
limited, you are not prohibited. Why would I have thought that? עשה
asei ולא תעשה הוא ואין עשה asei דוחה לא תעשה lo ta'asei
ועשה *assei ve-lo ta'assei hu ve-ein assei doche lo ta'assei ve-assei*. Let's
say you have a מצווה *mitzvah* to use the bird for the
טהרה *tahara* of the מצורע metzora. *metzora*. Okay, why would I have
thought without a פסוק *passuk* that you would not have been bound
by this prohibition? This prohibition is first of all a negative prohibition,
don't take the mother with the chicks or hovering over the chicks.
And number two, it's a positive מצווה *mitzvah*, you should send away
the mother. All I have, why I'm wanting to take it is
a positive מצווה *mitzvah* of using the birds for purifying the מצורע
metzora. *metzora*. That positive מצווה *mitzvah* can't override a negative and a
positive. We say a positive could override a negative, but it can't
override a negative and a positive. So how do I, why do
I need a פסוק *passuk*? Of course the מצווה *mitzvah* would not
be a license to go ahead and violate. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, לא צריכא דעבר ושקלה *lo tzricha de-avar ve-shaklah*. No, you
need it for a case דעבר ושקלה *de-avar ve-shaklah*. לאין *le-ein*, I
transgressed, I took the mother. דלאו עברי *de-lav avrei*, I've already transgressed
the negative prohibition, I took the mother. But I still have a
positive מצווה *mitzvah*, even after I've transgressed I can send away the
mother. Okay, so now עשה asei הוא דאיכא *assei hu de-ika*. I
still have a positive מצווה *mitzvah*, I can still at least send
away the mother after I've transgressed. So I might have thought ליתי
עשה ולדחי עשה *leisi assei ve-lidchi assei*. Let the positive מצווה *mitzvah*
that I need it for the מצורע metzora. *metzora* come and override
the positive מצווה *mitzvah* to send away the mother. Then at least
it's even, one versus one. We'll talk in a minute why I
would have thought that that would even if it is even, why
still would have thought it would have overridden, but at least there
it's even. קא משמע לן *kamashma lan*, therefore the verse teaches you
that no, that even there you're not allowed to, even there you
have to send it away. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says one
minute, הני למאן דתני le'man d'tani קיימו ולא קיימו kiymo v'lo kiymo
אלא למאן דתני ella le'man d'tani ביטלו ולא ביטלו bitlo v'lo bitlo,
*hani le-man de-tani kimei velo kimei ella le-man de-tani bitlo velo bitlo*.
So that's good if you say that what determines, now this is
a very important principle that is in מכות Makkot. *Makkos* and let
me just try to take a step back and explain it, actually
it's going to come up in the משנה Mishna *mishnah*, the next
משנה Mishna *mishnah* is, I think you're all also all familiar, this
is why the same way שילוח הקן *Shiluach HaKen* is interesting because
of the question of טעמי מצוות *ta'amei mitzvos*, it's also very interesting
because it's a central example, a prime example of the idea of
לאו הניתק לעשה *lav ha-nittak la-assei*. A negative commandment that is connected
to a positive מצווה *mitzvah* that is seemingly meant to fix it.
Okay, cause one way of reading it, how do you read the
verse? לא תקח האם על הבנים lo tikach ha'em al habanim שלח
תשלח Shaleach tishalach. את האם *lo tikach ha-em al ha-banim shaloch tishalach
es ha-em*. Do you read it as don't take them together, rather
what you should do is from the outset send away the mother.
I think that's how most of us would have read the verse.
That's how רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* reads the verse, that
the מצווה *mitzvah* is not about if you've transgressed, the מצווה *mitzvah*
of sending away is what you're supposed to do at the outset.
The rabbis however read it differently. Don't take them together, or don't
take even the mother, if you've taken them, here's what you can
do to fix it: send away the mother. That way reading it
the מצווה *mitzvah* of sending away is a ניתק *nittak*, is connected
to the negative prohibition and is a way of fixing the negative
prohibition. So according to that, if I took the mother bird I
don't get lashes because I have an option of fixing it. What's
my option of fixing it? Sending it away. That's a principle of
לאו *lav* that is connected to a מצוות עשה *mitzvas assei*, you
don't get lashes because the
עשה *assei* Well, okay, one minute. Now, what is, how do I
avoid lashes? So there's two גרסאות in a משנה that the גמרא
Gemara just discusses in מכות. Makkot One גרסא girsa is if I
am מקיים, mekayeim, קיימו לעשה, kiymo la'asei, if I fulfill the positive,
I don't get lashes. If I don't fulfill the positive, I do
get lashes. That's pretty straightforward. If I send away the mother bird,
I'm off. I at least fixed it. If I don't send away
the mother bird, then I violated without fixing it, I get lashes.
Another גרסא girsa in the גמרא Gemara there and the גמרא Gemara
there is a debate of אמוראים Amoraim which is the correct גרסא
girsa is ביטלו, bitlo, if I negated the positive מצוה, mitzvah, then
I get lashes. What would I have to do to negate the
positive מצוה? mitzvah? For example, kill the bird or or break its
wings. So if I actively make, you know, destroy the ability to
fix it. But לא ביטלו, lo bitlo, as long as I have
not actively destroyed negated the positive מצוה, mitzvah, as long as it's
possible to fulfill, even if I haven't fulfilled it, then I do
not get lashes. Okay? Now those are the scenarios. I should say,
by the way, that there's a lot of middle cases. What for
example is if I did not actually kill the bird, but it
died by itself? Okay? So I wasn't מבטל, mevatel, but it's no
longer possible to do. What would you say about that? On the
other רש"י Rashi also says that maybe one way of reading the
idea of קיימו kiymo is that not enough to fix it later.
You have to send it away תוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur.
If you waited to fix to send it away, then then we
don't give you a chance to fix it afterwards. Okay, so there's
a lot of different ways of interpreting what is the different ways
it could fix or I could not fix it. But but the
basic two camps are, the קיימו kiymo is most easily understood is
is that as long as I'm able to fulfill it, I fulfill
and I go ahead you give me a chance to fulfill it
and it gets me off the hook. If I'm choosing not to
or not able, then I get lashes. As opposed to ביטלו bitlo
which requires me to actively negate the ability to fulfill it and
otherwise I'm off the hook. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. You said that you took the mother bird and all you
have is a מצות עשה mitzvat asei because לא תעשה lo ta'asei
you already transgressed. So it says הניחא hani nicha that's good למאן
דתני קיימו ולא קיימו that the issue is whether I fulfill the
מצות עשה mitzvat asei or haven't fulfilled the מצות עשה mitzvat asei
yet. So therefore since right now I have not fulfilled the מצות
עשה, mitzvat asei, I've already transgressed the negative and all that I'm
left with is the positive מצוה. mitzvah. Okay? So therefore it's a
positive against a positive. אלא למאן דתני ביטלו bitlo ולא ביטלו, if
the point is that I am not even considered to have negated
to have transgressed the negative until I negate the positive, so כמה
דלא שחטה, kama d'lo shachta, as long as I haven't שחטed shacht
the mother bird, לא עבר אלאו, lo avar al lav, I haven't
even transgressed the negative. Right? That one says you don't even transgress
the negative until you also negate, actively negate the ability to do
the positive. So in that scenario even if I took the mother
bird, I haven't yet transgressed, so it still is you're telling me
that you want to use this bird for the מצורע, metzora, it's
an עשה against an עשה and a לא תעשה because to שחט
shacht it for מצורע would now be to transgress the negative. So
it's two against one. I I would obviously know you couldn't do
that. So the גמרא Gemara says ותו v'tu and in addition לרבי
יהודה דאמר שלח מעיקרא משמע, l'Rabbi Yehuda d'amar shallach mei'ikara mashma, we're
about to see in the next משנה that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says that שלח shelach is not to fix the negative. שלח means
you were supposed to have done it from the outset. So therefore
אפילו עשה נמי ליכא, afilu asei nami leika, according to him
then
then one minute, according to him what have I oh then I
don't even have an עשה left. Once I've taken it, I've transgressed
the negative, I haven't done the positive, so I you know so
that type of a scenario of course I could use it for
a קרבן korban because there's nothing standing in the way. So ממנפשך
mi-manafshach either I would have known that you can't use it for
a קרבן korban without a verse because it's a positive against a
positive and a negative, or according to רבי Rebbi, יהודה you should
be able to use it for a קרבן korban if you've actually
transgressed. אלא אמר מר בר רב אשי ella amar Mar bar Rav
Ashi סבר עבירה? savar aveira? Okay, that's a separate question, I'm not
going to talk about that now. אלא אמר מר בר רב אשי
ella amar Mar bar Rav Ashi כגון שנטלה על מנת לשלח. k'gon
shenetala al menat l'shallach. Now here is a very another interesting limit
and qualification on it. Let's say I took the mother bird with
the intent to send it away. Right? That normally would be a
natural part of the process. How do you do שלח תשלח? You
could just do it with your hand but you could also take
it and then go like that. Right? That's part of the process
of sending away. So if I took the mother bird with the
intent to send it away I have not transgressed anything yet. Right?
I'm part of doing part of the process. Then I changed my
mind. Now you can always trick but we're assuming you're not tricking.
Okay? If you're tricking, God knows. But you're not tricking. You're literally
changing your mind and saying you know what maybe I won't send
it away, maybe I'll use it for my קרבן korban for a
מצורע. So okay so in that type of a case I've never
the act of taking the mother bird has not transgressed לא תקח
האם על הבנים because in the act of taking, the initial act
of taking, it was allowed, it was part of sending it away.
We don't consider my changing of my mind right now to be
a new act of taking and a new transgression. So in that
way you actually again if you're sincere about it, okay you can
always trick, but in that way you you know finesse, you avoid
the whole transgression. So the גמרא Gemara says כגון שנטלה על מנת
לשלח, k'gon shenetala al menat l'shallach, דלאו ליכא עשה הוא דאיכא. d'lav
leika asei hu d'ika.
So you don't have the negative prohibition because there's no new transgression.
new act of taking, but you still have a positive מצוה mitzvah,
*mitzvah*, because even though you haven't taken the mother in a prohibited
way, you have a positive מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah* now of sending it
away, now that you, now that you are, you know, because you
always had that positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* when you took it over
the, over the nest. ולאו ועשה ודחי עשה *v'lav v'asei v'dachi asei*.
So I might have thought קום עשה דמצורע *kum asei d'metzora* and
override the עשה *asei* of sending away the mother bird here where
there's no negative prohibition in the, you know, in the offing. And
therefore the verse comes to teach me that you don't do it.
You don't use it for the מצורע *metzora*. So we finally constructed
a scenario where I would have had a הוה אמינא *hava amina*
you could, you would not be restricted if you have only the
מצות עשה mitzvot aseh, *mitzvot asei* and you have the עשה דמצורע
*asei d'metzora*. The עשה דמצורע *asei d'metzora* might override and the verse
tells me it doesn't. And now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* finally says,
and why would I have thought that? מאי אולמיה דהאי עשה מהאי
עשה *Mai ulmeih d'hai asei mehai asei*? Why would I have thought
the עשה דמצורע *asei d'metzora* was more powerful than the עשה *asei*
of sending away the mother bird?
Here's why. סלקא דעתך *Salka daitach*, I would have thought, הואיל ואמר
מר *ho'il v'amar mar*, since we teach, גדול שלום שבין איש לאשתו
*gadol shalom shebein ish l'ishto*, great is peace, you know, domestic tranquility,
peace between husband and wife. שהרי אמרה תורה שמו של הקדוש ברוך
הוא *sheharei amrah Torah shmo shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu*, normally it's שמי
*shmi* but here it's in third person, the Torah says that even
God's name שנכתב בקדושה *shenichtav bikdusha*, which is written in holiness on
the parchment of the סוטה *sotah*, right, that the parchment of the
סוטה *sotah* includes God's name, ימחה על המים *yimacheh al hamayim*, you
can scrape it into the water in order to, you know, resolve
the סוטה *sotah* problem and this woman that's been suspected and as
it's going to turn out unfairly suspected by her husband to deal,
you know, to basically, you know, push away all of the suspicions
and allow them to have, you know, to restore their marriage. So
that God is willing to even let His name be erased on
the water. So therefore והאי מצורע *v'hai metzora*, this מצורע *metzora*, כיון
דכמה דלא מטהר אסור בתשמיש המטה *keivan d'kamah d'lo mitaher assur b'tashmish
hamitah*, even though there's no real like, you know, sort of emotional
distance in the marriage, but practically they're not allowed not to be
having sex. A מצורע *metzora* is not allowed to have sex, דכתיב
*d'chtiv*, as it says, וישב מחוץ לאהלו שבעת ימים *v'yashav michutz l'ohalo
shivat yamim*, he has to sit outside of his tent for seven
days. And the דרשה *drasha* is אהלו זו אשתו *ohalo zo ishto*,
that the tent means his, you know, his domestic life with his
wife and his intimate life with his wife. מכאן שאסור בתשמיש המטה
*mikan she'assur b'tashmish hamitah*, here we see a מצורע *metzora* is not
allowed to have marital relations with his wife. So therefore, since he
is physically separated from his wife in this way, מהו דתימא *mahu
d'teima*, I might have thought, כיון דאסור בתשמיש המטה *keivan d'assur b'tashmish
hamitah*, since he has this prohibition and it's so important to bring
husband and wife together, ליתי עשה דידיה ולדחי עשה דשלוח הקן *leisei
asei dideih v'lidchi asei d'shiluach haken*, the positive מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of
him purifying himself is more important than the positive מצוה mitzvah, *mitzvah*
of sending away the mother bird. So I might have thought that,
קא משמע לן *ka mashma lan*, therefore the verse teaches that no,
this prohibition always holds. But actually the הוה אמינא *hava amina* now,
you know, after we did the technical way of figuring out how
you could have only a positive מצוה mitzvah. *mitzvah* without a negative
in terms of this, the הוה אמינא *hava amina* is a beautiful
הוה אמינא *hava amina* that I might have thought that yes, there
are values, but and this also gets to the values question. Here
at least you have some discussion. There are, you know, but there
are a lot of values. How do you determine what the hierarchy
of values are? At least here I would have had a הוה
אמינא *hava amina* that this is a greater value than the value
of sending away the mother bird. Of course then the question is,
that's such a lovely הוה אמינא *hava amina*, what's the מסקנא *maskana*?
Is the מסקנא *maskana* that the other thing is a more important
value or is the מסקנא *maskana*, well here maybe, you know, it's
not the same as the סוטה *sotah* case. Yes, they're not having
marital relations, but at least it's not like there's this suspicion and
hatred and so on and jealousy. Or maybe the point is is
that, like we were saying before, how much do we operate with
values and how much do we operate with sort of formal criteria?
And based on formal criteria, one מצות עשה mitzvot aseh *mitzvot asei*
doesn't override another מצות עשה *mitzvot asei*. So that actually is a
conclusion. I should also say that a fascinating thing is because of
the verse, you do not take the bird for the מצורע *metzora*.
Okay, because you would have thought you would, but send her away.
I mean, send her
away then take her later.
Yes, but it doesn't override this prohibition. Now I should have said,
I should say by the way, that it's a little strange because
normally when we say an עשה *asei* doesn't override a לא תעשה
ועשה *lo ta'asei v'asei*, we normally assume that the problem is that
it doesn't override the עשה *asei*, because an עשה *asei* overrides a
לא תעשה *lo ta'asei*, right? So normally when we say it doesn't
override a לא תעשה ועשה *lo ta'asei v'asei*, really what's getting in
the way is the עשה *asei*. So this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
a little funny because this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says if we could
get the לא תעשה *lo ta'asei* out of the picture, right, and
it's just an עשה *asei* against an עשה *asei*, then I might
think that one wins out over the other. Okay, so it's a
little funny because normally you would have thought the לא תעשה *lo
ta'asei* isn't even part of the whole, you know, lineup, the whole
because normally the עשה *asei* is able to override it. But here
we see no, that it would have been two against one that
also weighs. So even if one עשה *asei* against another עשה *asei*,
one would have been deemed as more weightier, if it's both the
עשה *asei* and the לא תעשה *lo ta'asei* combined, that made it,
that would have made it obvious that it does not override.
Yes, I was going to say, but you know, it would have
also depends on the timing, you know, because right now you literally
have the מצוה mitzvah? *mitzvah* of sending away, but the מצורע *metzora*,
you know,
well that's what I tried to draw the scenario, that there's no
other bird and there's no other whatever, but you're saying do it
later. But later, at least the way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* frames
it, means another day that husband and wife are not being together.
So at least that is at stake. Okay, but yes, the scenario
is very hard to understand. Let's take a look at the next
משנה *mishnah*. הנוטל אם על הבנים *Hanotel em al habanim*. So now
somebody... Actually, this we've already referred to, somebody transgresses and takes the
mother bird with the children, or when she was over the children.
רבי יהודה אומר לוקה ואינו משלח. You get lashes and you don't
have to send away, and sending away won't do any good, because
the idea of sending away was what you were supposed to do
rather than take it. It's not coming to address the scenario after
you took it. Okay, so you're done, you blew both mitzvos, you
get lashes. וחכמים אומרים, vechachamim omrim, no, משלח ואינו לוקה. meshale'ach ve'eino
loke. You send it away and you don't get lashes. Sending it
away is to fix the transgression of taking it, and therefore you
send it away and you do not get lashes. You still have
a מצוה, mitzvah, and by doing that מצוה, mitzvah, you don't get
lashes. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, this is the rule, כל מצות לא
תעשה שיש בה קום עשה, kol mitzvat lo ta'aseh sheyesh bah kum
aseh, any negative transgression that has in it a get up and
do, a positive מצוה mitzvah that is meant to fix it, אין
לוקין עליה, ein lokin aleha, you do not. And again, the question
is, do you not get lashes as long as you are fixing,
as long as you are doing the מצות עשה, as long as
you're sending it away? Or no, maybe you never get lashes unless
you actively negate it? That's the קימו kimo or the ביטלו question.
Why would you say actively negate it? Why don't you say until
it's no longer possible?
Right, that is a third possibility, and that might be within the
קימו kimo possibility. Yes, I'm talking about some extremes, and the גמרא
in מכות and the ראשונים Rishonim there deal with, you know, possible
of also middle positions. That is correct. Let's take a look.
בעי רבי אבא בר ממל, ba'ei Rabbi Abba bar Mammel, so Rabbi
Abba bar Mammel asked, טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דסבר לאו הניתק לעשה
לוקין עליו, ta'ama de'Rabbi Yehuda mishum desavar lav shenitak la'aseh lokin alav,
is his reason that he basically, it's a general debate with the
rabbis, not that how you interpret this verse? In general, he says
even if there's a מצות עשה that fixes it, you still get
lashes. He doesn't buy this whole thing that fixing it gets you
out of lashes. או דילמא, o dilma, or maybe
בעלמא סבר לאו הניתק לעשה אין לוקין עליו, be'alma savar lav shenitak
la'aseh ein lokin alav, normally he agrees to the principle. If it's
connected to a positive מצוה mitzvah. that fixes it, you don't get
lashes. והכא היינו טעמא, vehacha hainu ta'ama, here's why he debates in
this case of the bird, משום דקסבר שלח מעיקרא משמע, mishum dekasavar
shelach me'ikara mashma, שלח
means what you should have originally sent it away. So he just
argues in this application here, sending away is not meant to fix
the transgression, sending away is telling you what you should have done
at the outset, which I think is how we would have interpreted
the verse. Okay, תא שמע, ta shema, come in here. גנב וגזלן
ישנן בכלל מלקות, ganav vegazlan yeshnan bikhlal malkut, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. A גנב ganav and a גזלן gazlan get מלקות malkut
for stealing. So the גמרא says how could that be? והכא דלאו
הניתק לעשה הוא, vehacha delav shenitak la'aseh hu,
here there's a positive מצוה, mitzvah רחמנא אמר לא תגזול, Rachmana amar
lo tigzol, don't steal, and then it says והשיב את הגזילה, veheshiv
et hagezeila, return. And obviously that can't be מעיקרא, me'ikara, you can't
return the stolen object before you've stolen. So here clearly it's coming
to fix, and nevertheless he says you get lashes. So שמע מינה,
shma mina, you see, טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דקסבר לאו הניתק לעשה
לוקין עליו, ta'ama de'Rabbi Yehuda mishum dekasavar lav shenitak la'aseh lokin alav,
that he holds that even when there's a positive that fixes it,
you still get lashes. אמר ליה רבי זירא, amar leh Rabbi Zeira,
so Rabbi Zeira said back, לאו אמינא לכו, lav amina lechu, haven't
I told you guys, haven't I told you guys, כל מתניתא דלא
תניא בי רבי חייא ובי רבי אושעיא משבשתא. kol matnita d'lo tanya
be'Rebbi Chiyya u've'Rebbi Oshaya meshabbeshta.
This is a very important methodological point. Any ברייתא braita that has
not been edited by Rabbi Chiyya and Rabbi Oshaya, you can't trust
it. You have to assume it's a corrupt text. And if you
look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says why? Look at the first
רש"י, Rashi, רבי חייא ורבי אושעיא סידרו את הברייתות, Rebbi Chiyya ve'Rebbi
Oshaya sidru et habraitot,
they organized all of the ברייתות. braitot. They came right after רבי,
Rabbi Chiyya and Rabbi Oshaya, they're often assumed to be the authors
by the way of the תוספתא. Tosefta. So they edited and ordered
all of the ברייתות, braitot, ודקדקו בדברי כל חכם לומר כמו שאמר,
vedikdeku bedivrei kol chacham lomar k'mo she'amar, and they were very careful
making sure that they were accurate attributions. אבל יש תנאים הרבה, aval
yesh tanna'im harbeh,
there were many תנאים, tanna'im, this is small t תנאים, tanna'im, meaning
people who would say over ברייתות, braitot, who would repeat ברייתות, braitot,
who would be the like human books, the recorders of them, שמוסיפין
על משנתם בדידמי, shemosifin al mishnatam bedidami,
they would sort of like change the text based on their own
assumptions of what made sense. So you know, again, I've said this
before, Saul Lieberman had a great line, he said, you know, how
would they publish books in an oral culture? You'd figure out the
exact text you wanted to publish, you'd bring in people that were
excellent at memorizing, you'd tell them over your text, then you'd send
them to all the different communities and they would repeat it to
people and that's how you would publish your book. So that's what
were called the תנאים tanna'im with the low t, meaning not the
like Rabbi Meir תנא, tanna, but the memorizers of the ברייתא. braita.
And he said what you were looking for in that person, in
their job sort of qualifications, is an excellent memory and very little
creativity. Okay? Because if you're your own thinker, then you're going to
think, oh, you know what, it probably means this, and you're going
to modify it and you're going to insert your own stuff into
it. So that's what רש"י Rashi says. Therefore you cannot trust as
a general rule ברייתא, braita, because people made mistakes and they added
and they changed on their own, you know, thinking they were fixing
it. And the only things you can trust are the ones that
have been edited by Rabbi Chiyya and Rabbi Oshaya. So don't trust
that ברייתא braita that Rabbi Yehuda said that you get lashes for
גנב ganav and גזלן. gazlan. ולא תוסיפו מינה, velo tosifu minah, you
can't add any questions from it, בבי
מדרשא, be'vei midrasha, you can't ask from it in the בית מדרש.
beit midrash. דילמא אינה בכלל מלקות אלא תניא, dilma einah bikhlal malkut
ela tanya,
maybe the ברייתא braita said the exact opposite. Maybe it said that
Rabbi Yehuda says a גנב ganav and גזלן gazlan don't get מלקות,
malkut, but the person who was repeating this ברייתא braita connected that
Rabbi Yehuda with our Rabbi Yehuda and thought you always get מלקות.
malkut.
Okay, how did they know which ones were edited and which ones
weren't?
Apparently they did. And how do you know that once they edited
were not also, didn't get corrupted themselves one or two generations later?
So I don't know the answer to that. Okay, תא שמע *Ta
shema*. Okay, so right, come in here. דתניא רבי יאשיה ורבי חייא
*Detanya Rabbi Yoshia ve-Rabbi Chiya*. Ah, now you see the גמרא *Gemara*
in the next line says, okay, now you're going to be careful
what I quote. I've got a ברייתא Baraisa. *Braisa* that comes from
רבי חייא *Rabbi Chiya* and רבי יאשיה *Rabbi Yoshia*. And here's what
it says.
No, he means if they came from them, it means that they
have been, you know, they published it. Okay, so לא תשוב ושב
*Lo tashuv ve-shav*. What it says by, right, it says by שכחה
*shichcha*, do not go back and get the thing that you left,
the sheaf that you accidentally forgot. And let's say the person went
back and he actually picked up the שכחה *shichcha*, the sheaf that
he forgot. Or it says לא תחלה וחלה *Lo techaleh ve-chileh*, do
not cut the corners of your field, and he cut the corners
of his field, so he's transgressed the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, there's a
לא תעשה *lo sa'aseh* of שכחה *shichcha* leaving over and of פאה
*peah*. So do you get lashes? ישנן בכלל מלקות ארבעים *Yeshnan bikhlal
makkos arbaim*, you get lashes. דברי רבי יהודה *Divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. That's
what רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says. Now the problem is that the
verse says afterwards, it says לעני ולגר תעזוב אותם *Le-ani vela-ger ta'azov
osam*, leave them for the poor. So why doesn't רבי יהודה *Rabbi
Yehuda* say that that's you can now fix it by going back
and leaving it? So don't you see from here שמע מינה טעמא
דרבי יהודה משום דקסבר לאו שניתק לעשה לוקין עליו *shema mina ta'ama
de-Rabbi Yehuda mishum de-kasavar lav she-nitak le-aseh lokin alav*? That he says
that even though it has a positive מצוה *mitzvah* to fix it,
you still get lashes. Because here there's a positive מצוה *mitzvah* and
you get lashes. But says no, דילמא התם היינו טעמא דקסבר תעזוב
מעיקרא משמע *dilma hasam hainu ta'ama de-kasavar ta'azov me-ikara mashma*. Maybe there
he reads the verse just like he reads our verse. Right, I
think this is how we would have read the verse. Don't go
back and get the sheaf, leave it for the poor. It doesn't
mean if you transgress, then go back, then leave it. It means
rather leave it for the poor. So the same way he reads
by us rather send away the mother bird, here he reads rather
leave it for the poor. So in general, they say that no,
it's also, at least also coming to fix. Whether they also agree
that before I'll talk about in a minute. But anyway, so רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* might say in general if an עשה *aseh* fixes
it, then you're off from מלקות *makkos*, but here, like by the
mother bird, it means that you originally should have done that. Okay,
so let's keep on going. אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי *Amar leh
Ravina le-Rav Ashi*, תא שמע *Ta shema*. Okay, so right, come in
here. לא תותירו ממנו עד בוקר *Lo sosiru mimenu ad boker*, don't
leave over from the meat of a קרבן *korban* until the next
morning. והנותר ממנו עד בוקר באש תשרופו *Ve-ha-nosar mimenu ad boker ba-esh
tisrofu*, burn it in fire. בא הכתוב ליתן עשה אחר לא תעשה
*Ba ha-kasuv lisen aseh achar lo sa'aseh*, so you have a positive
thing fixing the negative. Obviously burning נותר *nosar* can only be done
after you've transgressed. You can't burn the נותר *nosar* before you've made
it into נותר *nosar*. So obviously it's coming after to fix it.
לומר לך שאין לוקין עליו *Lomar lach she-ein lokin alav*, to tell
you you don't get lashes. דברי רבי יהודה *Divrei Rabbi Yehuda*. The
words of רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda*. So here we have a ברייתא
Baraisa *Braisa* that רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* himself says that when we
know that it's coming to fix it and you fix it, you
don't get lashes. שמע מינה טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דקסבר שלח מעיקרא
משמע *Shema mina ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda mishum de-kasavar shalach me-ikara mashma*. Normally
he says when the עשה *aseh* fixes it, you don't get lashes,
but here שלח *shalach* means originally you should have sent it away.
אמר ליה רב עידי לרב אשי *Amar leh Rav Idi le-Rav Ashi*,
מתניתין נמי דיקא *matnisin nami dika*. That's also inferred from the language
of our משנה *Mishnah*. דקתני *De-kasani*, our משנה *Mishnah* says, הנוטל אם
על הבנים *ha-notel em al ha-banim*, if you take the mother with
the chicks, רבי יהודה אומר לוקה ואינו משלח *Rabbi Yehuda omer lokeh
ve-eino meshalach*, you get lashes and you don't send away. So it
sounds like there's no purpose, nothing is to be achieved by sending
it away. ואי סלקא דעתך טעמא דרבי יהודה משום דלאו שניתק לעשה
לוקין עליו *Ve-i salka dach-tach ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda mishum de-lav she-nitak le-aseh
lokin alav*, so if he says that no, no, he agrees that
there's a מצוה *mitzvah* to send away after you've taken, but he
just says it won't get you out of lashes, even with an
עשה *aseh* fixing it you don't get out of lashes. But if
he agrees that the שלח *shalach* means that you do it after
you've transgressed, so לוקה ומשלח מיבעי ליה *lokeh u-meshalach mibaye leh*, he
should have even gone further. He should have said you've got to
send it away, that's still your מצוה *mitzvah*, but it isn't going
to help you, you're still going to get lashes. But he doesn't
say that in the משנה *Mishnah*. In the משנה *Mishnah* he says
don't bother sending it away. So you see that the sending away
was only something that had applied before at the outset, doesn't apply
according to him after you've transgressed. Okay, ואי סלקא דעתך *ve-i salka
dach-tach*, I just read it. So the גמרא *Gemara* says no, ודילמא
הכי קאמר במתניתין *ve-dilma hachi ka'amar be-matnisin*, maybe this is what our
משנה *Mishnah* means. אין נפטר עד דמלקין ליה *Ein niftar ad de-malkin
leh*, what our משנה *Mishnah* might mean is that it won't help
you to send it away. It doesn't mean don't send it away.
Maybe it could have been read to say yes, you're supposed to
send it away, but it isn't going to help you. So you
can't prove it from the משנה *Mishnah*. But even though you can't
prove it from the משנה *Mishnah*, what we are saying is that
רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* generally says that if a מצות עשה *mitzvas
aseh* is coming to fix the לא תעשה *lo sa'aseh*, you don't
get lashes. Again, whether you have to actively fix it or not
is not clear. But what is debatable is, but what he argues
on is whether the מצוה *mitzvah* of שלח *shalach* means whether you,
he says there it does not mean do it after you've transgressed,
but it only applies before at the outset you're supposed to send
away. The rabbis say it means after you've transgressed. Now the one
question, well, which I'll get to tomorrow I guess, that we have
to answer according to the rabbis is, do they say it only
means after you've transgressed, or do they agree that the מצות עשה
*mitzvas aseh* applies even before you've transgressed? Okay? So, right, רבי יהודה
*Rabbi Yehuda* says it only applies before. The rabbis say it even
applies after to fix the transgression. Do they agree that there's a
positive מצוה *mitzvah* of sending away if you're not transgressing? Okay, and
do you do the positive מצוה *mitzvah* by sending away. Keep that
question in mind, we will touch on it. Okay, so the next
משנה says, שלח תשלח את האם ואת הבנים תקח לך. Shaleach tishalach
es ha'eim v'es habanim tikach lach. Even for
a מצוה. What does that mean? Even for a מצוה? The גמרא
explains, even if you're taking the birds for a מצורע. You need
birds to purify a מצורע. So you might think, since I'm doing
a מצוה, I don't have to send the mother away. The משנה
says, no, even for a מצוה, you have to send her away.
Now, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, the
מצוה of שלוח הקן shiluach haken only applies if you want the
children. If you don't want the children, you don't have to send
the mother away. The גמרא asks, but the משנה says even for
a מצוה. If you're taking the birds for a מצורע, you want
the children. So of course you have to send the mother away.
What if you don't want the children at all? You just want
to do the מצוה of שלוח הקן. shiluach haken. רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda says you don't have to. But the גמרא brings a מיתיבי,
meisivi, an objection from a ברייתא. שלח תשלח. Why the double language?
To include even if you don't want the children. This contradicts רב
יהודה. Rav Yehuda. The גמרא answers, that ברייתא is according to the
תנא Tanna who says the מצוה is independent of wanting the children.
But רב יהודה Rav Yehuda follows the other תנא. Tanna.